<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: News | bio4j]]></title>
  <link href="http://bio4j.com/blog/categories/news/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bio4j.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-19T15:40:00+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://bio4j.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[oh no sequences!]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bio4j goes to GSoC mentor summit 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://bio4j.com/blog/2014/10/bio4j-goes-to-gsoc-mentor-summit-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-29T17:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://bio4j.com/blog/2014/10/bio4j-goes-to-gsoc-mentor-summit-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/bio4jGsoc.png"></p>

<p>I just got home yesterday from San Francisco after attending together with <a href="https://twitter.com/eparejatobes">@eparejatobes</a> to the 10th edition of the Google Summer of Code mentor summit. It’s been a great experience that I would like to share with you all in this blog post ;)
For those of you who still don’t know what <a href="https://developers.google.com/open-source/soc/?csw=1">GSoC</a> is, here’s a debrief:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Google Summer of Code is a program that offers student developers stipends to write code for various open source projects. We work with many open source, free software, and technology-related groups to identify and fund projects over a three month period. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>This was Bio4j’s first year as a GSoC organization and we got three students who worked in the following projects:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/dynamograph">dynamograph</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/exporter">exporter</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/el-grafo">el-grafo</a></li>
</ul>

<p>It also was my first experience as a mentor and I must say that I both learned and enjoyed it a lot during the process.</p>

<p>The events started on Friday with a complimentary visit to the theme park <em>Great America</em>, nice! followed by a really cool dinner reception at the <a href="http://www.thetech.org/">San Jose Tech Museum of Innovation</a> where we had surprise speakers such as Linus Torvals plus the opportunity of exploring the geeky exhibits from the museum while having some drinks.</p>

<p>We were supposed to dress smart for a change, which was interesting, seeing all these people wearing nice clothes :)</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/fotoTechMuseum.jpg" width="280"></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I must say that I had to watch around 20 minutes of youtube videos before I managed to get the knot tie right… xD</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sessions started early the next day with more than eight simultaneous rooms <em>(without taking into account the impromptu sessions that were organized at the ballroom from time to time)</em> and went on till the evening.</p>

<p>It was the first time that I went to an <strong><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unconference">unconference</a></strong> and I just loved it. 
It is actually great to have the opportunity to explore the different sessions and meet up with people on the way spontaneously, without all the rigidity that so many times comes with <em>“standard”</em> conferences. </p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/stickers.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>Meeting in person people from the <a href="http://www.reactome.org/">Reactome database</a> project was cool since we plan to include this data source into Bio4j in the near future. It was also nice to see in person some of the guys that I’ve been following on twitter for a while like <a href="https://twitter.com/braincode">@braincode</a> among others.
I also found a good idea the fact of having both the sticker exchange table and the tea-room filled with chocolates from all over the world! The day ended with a quiz show that I unfortunately couldn’t join but, I read on twitter that it was quite funny.</p>

<p>On Sunday we opened the day with a trip to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Googleplex">Googleplex</a> where we could see the actual place where the Google folks work on.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/chocolates.png" width="240"></p>

<p>There was some time left for a couple more sessions and then we unfortunately had to say bye to all the new acquaintances we made after attending the closing session at the hotel. </p>

<p>I would like to end this post by thanking all the people that helped out on the organization of this awesome summit.
Also a special thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/fossygrl">@fossygirl</a>, great job!</p>

<p>Stay tuned for the next post, we will be releasing a shiny new version of Bio4j based on Titan very soon ;)</p>

<p><img src="/images/fotoGoogleAndroid.png"></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/pablopareja">@pablopareja</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bio4j accepted for Google Summer of Code 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://bio4j.com/blog/2014/02/bio4j-accepted-for-google-summer-of-code-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-25T17:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://bio4j.com/blog/2014/02/bio4j-accepted-for-google-summer-of-code-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/GoogleSummer_2014logo.jpg" width="300" height="270"></p>

<p>We are really excited to announce that <strong>Bio4j</strong> has been <strong>accepted</strong> as a <a href="https://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/org2/google/gsoc2014/bio4j">mentoring organization</a> for <strong><a href="https://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/homepage/google/gsoc2014">Google Summer of Code 2014</a></strong>. This was the first year we applied for it, and it feels just great being part of this inititative!</p>

<p>We think this is a great opportunity for students, giving them the opportunity to hack on pretty cool stuff around graph databases, bio big data and cloud computing.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-participate">how to participate</h2>

<p>If this sounds amazing and you are a student (PhD, masters, undergraduate, <a href="https://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/document/show/gsoc_program/google/gsoc2014/help_page#2._Whos_eligible_to_participate_as_a">whatever</a>) or know someone who is,</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/gsoc14/wiki/ideas">check our ideas list</a></strong> and then</li>
  <li><strong>contact a potential mentor</strong> or if you don’t know who just <a href="https://github.com/eparejatobes">@eparejatobes</a> or <a href="https://github.com/pablopareja">@pablopareja</a></li>
</ol>

<p>You can read more about it in the <a href="https://github.com/bio4j/gsoc14/wiki">bio4j/gsoc14 wiki</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Berkeley Phylogenomics Group receives an NSF grant to develop a graph DB for Big Data challenges in genomics building on Bio4j]]></title>
    <link href="http://bio4j.com/blog/2013/11/new-bio4j-success-berkeley-phylogenomics-grant/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-12T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://bio4j.com/blog/2013/11/new-bio4j-success-berkeley-phylogenomics-grant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://phylogenomics.berkeley.edu/">Sjölander Lab</a> at the <a href="http://www.berkeley.edu/index.html">University of California, Berkeley</a>, has recently been awarded a <strong>250K</strong> US dollars <em>EAGER</em> grant from the National Science Foundation to build a graph database for Big Data challenges in genomics.  Naturally, <strong>they’re building on Bio4j</strong>.</p>

<p>The project “<strong>EAGER: Towards a self-organizing map and hyper-dimensional information network for the human genome</strong>” aims to create a graph database of genome and proteome data for the human genome and related species to allow biologists and computational biologists to mine the information in gene family trees, biological networks and other graph data that cannot be represented effectively in relational databases. For these goals, they will develop on top of the pioneering graph-based bioinformatics platform <strong>Bio4j</strong>. </p>

<p>”<em>We are excited to see how Bio4j is used by top research groups to build cutting-edge bioinformatics solutions</em>” said <strong>Eduardo Pareja</strong>, <strong><a href="http://www.era7bioinformatics.com">Era7 Bioinformatics</a> CEO</strong>. “<em>To reach an even broader user base, we are pleased to announce that we now provide versions for both Neo4j and Titan graph databases, for which we have developed another layer of abstraction for the domain model using Blueprints</em>.”</p>

<p>”<em>EAGER stands for Early-concept Grants for Exploratory Research</em>”, explained <strong>Professor Kimmen Sjölander</strong>, <strong>head of the <a href="http://phylogenomics.berkeley.edu/">Berkeley Phylogenomics Group</a></strong>: “<em>NSF awards these grants to support exploratory work in its early stages on untested, but potentially transformative, research ideas or approaches</em>”. “<em>My lab’s focus is on machine learning methods for Big Data challenges in biology, particularly for graphical data such as gene trees, networks, pathways and protein structures. The limitations of relational database technologies for graph data, particularly BIG graph data, restrict scientists’ ability to get any real information from that data. When we decided to switch to a graph database, we did a lot of research into the options. When we found out about Bio4j, we knew we’d found our solution. The Bio4j team has made our development tasks so much easier, and we look forward to a long and fruitful collaboration in this open-source project</em>”.</p>

<p>You can find more information here:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://era7bioinformatics.com/en/download_file.cfm?file=1695&amp;news=17"><strong>PHYLOGENOMICS_BERKELEY_BIO4J_ERA7_BIOINFORMATICS.pdf</strong></a></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/pablopareja"><strong>@pablopareja</strong></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
