<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: News | bio4j]]></title>
  <link href="http://bio4j.com/blog/categories/news/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bio4j.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-03-22T20:26:30+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://bio4j.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[oh no sequences!]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bio4j preprint available]]></title>
    <link href="http://bio4j.com/blog/2015/03/bio4j-preprint-available/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-22T18:20:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://bio4j.com/blog/2015/03/bio4j-preprint-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A citable preprint in the <a href="http://biorxiv.org/">bioRxiv</a> describing Bio4j went online yesterday:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong><a href="http://biorxiv.org/content/early/2015/03/20/016758">Bio4j: a high-performance cloud-enabled graph-based data platform</a></strong></li>
</ul>

<p>It serves (we hope) as a good introduction to what is Bio4j, and what it has to offer; especially so if, for getting a general idea of Bio4j, you would rather read prose than code. If you are using Bio4j for something that you want to publish, citing it is much easier now: all bioRxiv preprints are assigned a DOI. Comments, thoughts, opinions are all more than welcome! We will submit a paper based on this preprint to an open access journal. For completeness, here’s the citation info and the abstract:</p>

<hr />
<p><br /></p>

<h3 id="bio4j-a-high-performance-cloud-enabled-graph-based-data-platform">Bio4j: a high-performance cloud-enabled graph-based data platform</h3>

<p><em>Pablo Pareja-Tobes, Raquel Tobes, Marina Manrique, Eduardo Pareja, Eduardo Pareja-Tobes</em> <br />
<strong>bioRxiv</strong> – <strong>doi</strong>: <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/016758">10.1101/016758</a></p>

<!-- ### Abstract -->

<p><strong>Background.</strong> Next Generation Sequencing and other high-throughput technologies have brought a revolution to the bioinformatics landscape, by offering sheer amounts of data about previously unaccessible domains in a cheap and scalable way. However, fast, reproducible, and cost-effective data analysis at such scale remains elusive. A key need for achieving it is being able to access and query the vast amount of publicly available data, specially so in the case of knowledge-intensive, semantically rich data: incredibly valuable information about proteins and their functions, genes, pathways, or all sort of biological knowledge encoded in ontologies remains scattered, semantically and physically fragmented.</p>

<p><strong>Methods and Results.</strong> Guided by this, we have designed and developed Bio4j. It aims to offer a platform for the integration of semantically rich biological data using typed graph models. We have modeled and integrated most publicly available data linked with proteins into a set of interdependent graphs. Data querying is possible through a data model aware Domain Specific Language implemented in Java, letting the user write typed graph traversals over the integrated data. A ready to use cloud-based data distribution, based on the Titan graph database engine is provided; generic data import code can also be used for in-house deployment.</p>

<p><strong>Conclusion.</strong> Bio4j represents a unique resource for the current Bioinformatician, providing at once a solution for several key problems: data integration; expressive, high performance data access; and a cost-effective scalable cloud deployment model.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bio4j: updates]]></title>
    <link href="http://bio4j.com/blog/2015/03/bio4j-updates/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-11T17:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://bio4j.com/blog/2015/03/bio4j-updates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We’ve spent the past few months working <em>really</em> hard on Bio4j. There has not been a lot of updates here basically because there were too many new things happening :) </p>

<p>But now things are stabilizing and it’s about time we start to introduce all the new features and improvements we have in store. In this first post I just want to give an overview of Bio4j’s current state, going into more detail in subsequent posts.</p>

<h2 id="bio4j-now">Bio4j now</h2>

<h3 id="a-new-graph-schema-and-api">A new graph schema and API</h3>

<p>We have now a strongly typed graph schema and traversal API in <strong><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/bio4j">bio4j/bio4j</a></strong>, based on <strong><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/angulillos">angulillos</a></strong> (more about angulillos later). With it, you can write traversals over Bio4j data abstractly, and then execute them over any implementation. These queries are checked to be correct both structurally (no source of a vertex) and with respect to the Bio4j schema. Vertices and edges are now part of graphs, which can declare dependencies; writing your own extensions to the model is now much easier than before. As part of these changes we did a thorough graph-per-graph review of the Bio4j model, which resulted in some significant improvements.</p>

<p>Of course a schema is not that useful without actual data conforming to it; we also wrote generic importers for all graphs. These importers can be executed using any implementation of the angulillos API.</p>

<h3 id="a-titan-based-implementation-and-data-distribution">A Titan-based implementation and data distribution</h3>

<p>With much of the work already done at the level of bio4j/bio4j, providing a data distribution of Bio4j becomes pretty simple; you just need to</p>

<ol>
  <li>implement angulillos for your database technology of choice; this is what you have for <a href="http://thinkaurelius.github.io/titan/">Titan</a> in <strong><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/angulillos-titan">angulillos-titan</a></strong>.</li>
  <li>if your database has support for type definitions and schemas, create those corresponding to the Bio4j schema; what we do for each graph in <strong><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/bio4j-titan">bio4j-titan</a></strong></li>
</ol>

<p>We finished running the importing process for all graphs just a few hours ago. A pretty sizable <code>.tar</code> containing all the Titan files is available from an S3 bucket. With that you just need to spin an EC2 instance, download and extract that and start using Bio4j. Or, if you don’t want to use AWS, you can of course run the import process on your own infrastructure.</p>

<h3 id="angulillos-generic-typed-property-graphs-in-java">Angulillos: generic typed property graphs in Java</h3>

<p>Writing <em>correct</em> queries for Bio4j was becoming harder and harder as we integrated more databases and resources, and we had no way of expressing the graph schemas, even for documentation purposes. That is what <strong><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/angulillos">angulillos</a></strong> strives to solve. You can think of angulillos as a strongly typed version of the property graph model: first you describe a graph schema in terms of types, and then you can write generic traversals over it, which are guaranteed to be well-typed. This means that for example</p>

<ul>
  <li>you cannot retrieve the outgoing edges of and edge</li>
  <li>and you can get the tweets that a user tweeted, but not the users that a tweet follows!</li>
</ul>

<p>The API is really straightforward to implement, and its only dependency is Java 8 (for Streams and lambdas). <strong><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/angulillos-titan">angulillos-titan</a></strong> can serve as an example of how this can be done.</p>

<h3 id="the-future">The future</h3>

<p>The next post will be dedicated to a tentative roadmap, explaining what we are working on now; A (really nice) Scala API, data distribution and AWS deployment improvements, and new integrations of genomic data sources are coming in the following months!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bio4j goes to GSoC mentor summit 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://bio4j.com/blog/2014/10/bio4j-goes-to-gsoc-mentor-summit-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-29T17:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://bio4j.com/blog/2014/10/bio4j-goes-to-gsoc-mentor-summit-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/bio4jGsoc.png"></p>

<p>I just got home yesterday from San Francisco after attending together with <a href="https://twitter.com/eparejatobes">@eparejatobes</a> to the 10th edition of the Google Summer of Code mentor summit. It’s been a great experience that I would like to share with you all in this blog post ;)
For those of you who still don’t know what <a href="https://developers.google.com/open-source/soc/?csw=1">GSoC</a> is, here’s a debrief:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Google Summer of Code is a program that offers student developers stipends to write code for various open source projects. We work with many open source, free software, and technology-related groups to identify and fund projects over a three month period. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>This was Bio4j’s first year as a GSoC organization and we got three students who worked in the following projects:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/dynamograph">dynamograph</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/exporter">exporter</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/el-grafo">el-grafo</a></li>
</ul>

<p>It also was my first experience as a mentor and I must say that I both learned and enjoyed it a lot during the process.</p>

<p>The events started on Friday with a complimentary visit to the theme park <em>Great America</em>, nice! followed by a really cool dinner reception at the <a href="http://www.thetech.org/">San Jose Tech Museum of Innovation</a> where we had surprise speakers such as Linus Torvals plus the opportunity of exploring the geeky exhibits from the museum while having some drinks.</p>

<p>We were supposed to dress smart for a change, which was interesting, seeing all these people wearing nice clothes :)</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/fotoTechMuseum.jpg" width="280"></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I must say that I had to watch around 20 minutes of youtube videos before I managed to get the knot tie right… xD</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sessions started early the next day with more than eight simultaneous rooms <em>(without taking into account the impromptu sessions that were organized at the ballroom from time to time)</em> and went on till the evening.</p>

<p>It was the first time that I went to an <strong><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unconference">unconference</a></strong> and I just loved it. 
It is actually great to have the opportunity to explore the different sessions and meet up with people on the way spontaneously, without all the rigidity that so many times comes with <em>“standard”</em> conferences. </p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/stickers.jpg" width="260"></p>

<p>Meeting in person people from the <a href="http://www.reactome.org/">Reactome database</a> project was cool since we plan to include this data source into Bio4j in the near future. It was also nice to see in person some of the guys that I’ve been following on twitter for a while like <a href="https://twitter.com/braincode">@braincode</a> among others.
I also found a good idea the fact of having both the sticker exchange table and the tea-room filled with chocolates from all over the world! The day ended with a quiz show that I unfortunately couldn’t join but, I read on twitter that it was quite funny.</p>

<p>On Sunday we opened the day with a trip to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Googleplex">Googleplex</a> where we could see the actual place where the Google folks work on.</p>

<p><img class="right" src="/images/chocolates.png" width="240"></p>

<p>There was some time left for a couple more sessions and then we unfortunately had to say bye to all the new acquaintances we made after attending the closing session at the hotel. </p>

<p>I would like to end this post by thanking all the people that helped out on the organization of this awesome summit.
Also a special thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/fossygrl">@fossygirl</a>, great job!</p>

<p>Stay tuned for the next post, we will be releasing a shiny new version of Bio4j based on Titan very soon ;)</p>

<p><img src="/images/fotoGoogleAndroid.png"></p>

<p><a href="https://twitter.com/pablopareja">@pablopareja</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bio4j accepted for Google Summer of Code 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://bio4j.com/blog/2014/02/bio4j-accepted-for-google-summer-of-code-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-25T17:18:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://bio4j.com/blog/2014/02/bio4j-accepted-for-google-summer-of-code-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="right" src="/images/GoogleSummer_2014logo.jpg" width="300" height="270"></p>

<p>We are really excited to announce that <strong>Bio4j</strong> has been <strong>accepted</strong> as a <a href="https://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/org2/google/gsoc2014/bio4j">mentoring organization</a> for <strong><a href="https://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/homepage/google/gsoc2014">Google Summer of Code 2014</a></strong>. This was the first year we applied for it, and it feels just great being part of this inititative!</p>

<p>We think this is a great opportunity for students, giving them the opportunity to hack on pretty cool stuff around graph databases, bio big data and cloud computing.</p>

<h2 id="how-to-participate">how to participate</h2>

<p>If this sounds amazing and you are a student (PhD, masters, undergraduate, <a href="https://www.google-melange.com/gsoc/document/show/gsoc_program/google/gsoc2014/help_page#2._Whos_eligible_to_participate_as_a">whatever</a>) or know someone who is,</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong><a href="https://github.com/bio4j/gsoc14/wiki/ideas">check our ideas list</a></strong> and then</li>
  <li><strong>contact a potential mentor</strong> or if you don’t know who just <a href="https://github.com/eparejatobes">@eparejatobes</a> or <a href="https://github.com/pablopareja">@pablopareja</a></li>
</ol>

<p>You can read more about it in the <a href="https://github.com/bio4j/gsoc14/wiki">bio4j/gsoc14 wiki</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Berkeley Phylogenomics Group receives an NSF grant to develop a graph DB for Big Data challenges in genomics building on Bio4j]]></title>
    <link href="http://bio4j.com/blog/2013/11/new-bio4j-success-berkeley-phylogenomics-grant/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-12T12:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://bio4j.com/blog/2013/11/new-bio4j-success-berkeley-phylogenomics-grant</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="http://phylogenomics.berkeley.edu/">Sjölander Lab</a> at the <a href="http://www.berkeley.edu/index.html">University of California, Berkeley</a>, has recently been awarded a <strong>250K</strong> US dollars <em>EAGER</em> grant from the National Science Foundation to build a graph database for Big Data challenges in genomics.  Naturally, <strong>they’re building on Bio4j</strong>.</p>

<p>The project “<strong>EAGER: Towards a self-organizing map and hyper-dimensional information network for the human genome</strong>” aims to create a graph database of genome and proteome data for the human genome and related species to allow biologists and computational biologists to mine the information in gene family trees, biological networks and other graph data that cannot be represented effectively in relational databases. For these goals, they will develop on top of the pioneering graph-based bioinformatics platform <strong>Bio4j</strong>. </p>

<p>”<em>We are excited to see how Bio4j is used by top research groups to build cutting-edge bioinformatics solutions</em>” said <strong>Eduardo Pareja</strong>, <strong><a href="http://www.era7bioinformatics.com">Era7 Bioinformatics</a> CEO</strong>. “<em>To reach an even broader user base, we are pleased to announce that we now provide versions for both Neo4j and Titan graph databases, for which we have developed another layer of abstraction for the domain model using Blueprints</em>.”</p>

<p>”<em>EAGER stands for Early-concept Grants for Exploratory Research</em>”, explained <strong>Professor Kimmen Sjölander</strong>, <strong>head of the <a href="http://phylogenomics.berkeley.edu/">Berkeley Phylogenomics Group</a></strong>: “<em>NSF awards these grants to support exploratory work in its early stages on untested, but potentially transformative, research ideas or approaches</em>”. “<em>My lab’s focus is on machine learning methods for Big Data challenges in biology, particularly for graphical data such as gene trees, networks, pathways and protein structures. The limitations of relational database technologies for graph data, particularly BIG graph data, restrict scientists’ ability to get any real information from that data. When we decided to switch to a graph database, we did a lot of research into the options. When we found out about Bio4j, we knew we’d found our solution. The Bio4j team has made our development tasks so much easier, and we look forward to a long and fruitful collaboration in this open-source project</em>”.</p>

<p>You can find more information here:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://era7bioinformatics.com/en/download_file.cfm?file=1695&amp;news=17"><strong>PHYLOGENOMICS_BERKELEY_BIO4J_ERA7_BIOINFORMATICS.pdf</strong></a></li>
</ul>

<p><a href="http://twitter.com/pablopareja"><strong>@pablopareja</strong></a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
